宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
（ナレーション）宇宙開発の
結果として出た廃棄物―
Space debris, refuse generated during space
station construction, is a very serious threat.
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
これは 2075年―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
♪～
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance
（ラビィ）
だからさ そこをもう少し―
Come on, can't I talk you
into going a little lower?
ほんの:mere/only/just, 曲げる[まげる]:to bend|to lean|to bend (the truth)||, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
ほんのちょっと
曲げてもらえないかなあ
課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 予算[よさん]:estimate/budget, 少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce
うちの課 予算 少ないのよ
My section doesn't have
much of a budget.
オーバーホール:overhaul
（整備士）オーバーホールでしょ？
This is an overhaul
we're talking about.
交換[こうかん]:exchange/interchange/switching, パーツ:part/component, 特注[とくちゅう]:special order (goods)/custom (made)/bespoke
交換パーツだって特注だし
Plus, the replacement parts
are all special-order.
かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum, 買い換える[かいかえる]:to buy a replacement/to replace by buying something new, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient
もう いいかげん買い換えたら？
こんな古いの
Why don't you get rid of this relic
and buy a new one?
予算[よさん]:estimate/budget
（ラビィ）だから
予算がないって言ってるじゃない
I just said that we've got
no budget, didn't I?
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
ねえ 頼むよ
Come on, please!
I'll introduce
you to some great bars!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 店[みせ]:store/shop/establishment, 店[てん]:-store/-shop, 案内[あんない]:information/guidance|to guide
今度 いい店 案内するしさ
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, ウサギ:rabbit/hare/coney, 競争[きょうそう]:competition/contest|to compete
ほら 日本式のウサギが出てきて
カメと競争するやつ
I know a Japanese-style place where they've
got this rabbit that races a tortoise.
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, ウサギ:rabbit/hare/coney, 競争[きょうそう]:competition/contest|to compete
ほら 日本式のウサギが出てきて
カメと競争するやつ
フィー:phi
（ユーリ）
フィーさん どこへ？
- Fee-san? Where are you going?
日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, ウサギ:rabbit/hare/coney, 競争[きょうそう]:competition/contest|to compete
ほら 日本式のウサギが出てきて
カメと競争するやつ
I'm gonna head out
for a smoke.
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
（フィー）タバコ 吸ってくる
Hey! Our contract
isn't over yet!
契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
おい！
まだ契約 終わってないんだぞ！
吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
（フィー）４日も吸ってないし―
I haven't had a smoke
in four days,
会計[かいけい]:account/finance/accountant, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
それに会計は
係長補佐の仕事だろう？
...and this bean counting stuff is your job,
right, Mr. Assistant Manager?
I'll leave you to it!
まっか:bright red/deep red|downright (e.g. lie)
まっかせるよー
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
♪～
Phase 12
A Modest Request
（コートの男）んっ
３ ２ １
Three... Two... One...
（フィー）なっ…
（フィー）あ… ああ…
Boy, you sure
got lucky.
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
（作業員）
いやあ 危ないとこだったね
爆破[ばくは]:destructive blast/blowing up/explosion
（作業員）
爆破テロがあったんだよ  ここで
There was a terrorist
bombing here.
近頃[ちかごろ]:lately/recently/nowadays, 話題[わだい]:topic/subject
チェッ…
ほら あれだ 近頃 話題のやつ
It was those guys who've been in the news
lately. Those Space Defense Front guys.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
宇宙防衛戦線とかいう
Are you a smoker? Better be careful.
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
あんた タバコ 吸うの？
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
気をつけなよ
Their favorite stunt lately is planting
bombs in smoking rooms.
喫煙室[きつえんしつ]:smoking room/smoking compartment, 爆弾[ばくだん, バクダン]:bomb|alcohol with liquor added (esp. wine-based shochu highball, also beer with whiskey), 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), おはこ:one's favourite party trick (favorite)/one's specialty|No. 18
やつら 喫煙室に
爆弾 仕掛けるのが おはこだから
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
くっ… 宇宙防衛戦線…
The Space Defense Front...
The prevailing opinion is that
the Space Defense Front...
月面[げつめん]:moon's surface, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 爆破[ばくは]:destructive blast/blowing up/explosion, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related
（アナウンサー）
月面都市爆破に関しては―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 犯行[はんこう]:crime/criminal act/offence
宇宙防衛戦線の犯行であると…
...is behind these bombings
in lunar surface cities...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
（課長）宇宙防衛戦線？
Space Defense Front?
Those guys who say that humanity
never should have come into space.
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
（ハチマキ）人類は宇宙に
出るべきじゃなかったって―
連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe
言ってる連中だよ
（課長）そんなこといっても
もう出ちゃったのに
What good does saying that now do?
We're already here.
That's why they say we should smash
everything that's out in space, get it?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
（ハチマキ）
だから宇宙に出たものを
全部 壊しちまおうってんだろ？
セブン:seven, 狙う[ねらう]:to aim at
（課長）じゃあ
このセブンも狙われてるの？
Then... Is Seven
a target, too?
（ハチマキ）さあな
Beats me.
それより俺が聞きたいのは
なんで俺たちが―
What I really wanna know is,
how come we gotta clean up...
商品[しょうひん]:commodity/article of commerce/goods, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 発注[はっちゅう]:ordering (materials)/placing an order/order, 尻拭い[しりぬぐい]:cleaning up or covering for another/bearing the consequences of someone else's error/paying a debt for someone
商品課の発注ミスの尻拭いを
せにゃならんのだ
...after Merchandising Section when
they screwed up their own order?!
Don't complain. We're in
the red again this month,
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase
（課長）文句 言わない
今月[こんげつ]:this month, 赤字[あかじ]:deficit|red text|corrections (by a teacher or proofreader) written in red
うちは今月も赤字だし―
オーバーホール:overhaul, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room
ToyBox(トイボックス)を
オーバーホールしてる間は―
...and while Toy Box is in for her overhaul,
none of us has anything to do.
みんな やることないでしょ？
If I knew I'd be stuck doing this, I would've
gone to the moon with the others.
フィー:phi, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
（ハチマキ）こんなんだったら
フィーたちと一緒に―
月 行くんだったよ
And where the hell
is Tanabe, anyway?!
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||
第一 タナベはどうした！
Oh, Ai-chan? She took
the day off.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, お休み[おやすみ]:holiday|sleep|Good night
（課長）愛(あい)ちゃんなら お休み
How come?
なんで？
What was it for again?
何だっけ？
E-chan? What was it
for again?
エーちゃん なんでだっけ？
デート:date/go on a date
（エーデル）
デートじゃないでしょうか？
For a date, I think.
あっ
そうなの？
What, really?!
She asked me to
recommend a boutique.
ブティック:boutique, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（エーデル）ブティックの場所
聞かれましたから
A date? With who?
デート:date/go on a date
（課長）デートって誰と？
Should I have
gotten confirmation?
確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 事項[じこう]:matter/item/facts
（エーデル）
確認事項でしたでしょうか？
No, if you don't know,
that's fine.
（課長）いや
知らないんならいいんだけどさ
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
そうか
愛ちゃんも女の子だもんなあ
So, I guess our little Ai-chan is a woman, too...
（チェンシン）ハチ！
Even if you tell me to give
her back later, I won't.
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
あとから返せって言われても
返せないぞ
（ハチマキ）ああ…
相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
（課長）ねえ ハッちゃん
相手 誰か知ってる？
Say, Ha-chan, do you know
who she's going out with?
知らねえよ！
How should I know?!
A boy who joined up at the
same time as her, maybe?
同期[どうき]:same period|same year (of graduation, entering a company, etc.)|synchronization
同期の子かな
Or maybe she's been seeing someone
ever since she was on Earth.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
それとも地球にいたころから
つきあってる相手がいたとか
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety
まさか不倫じゃ…
It couldn't be an affair,
could it?
外れる[はずれる]:to be disconnected/to get out of place/to be off
（リュシー）どれも外れでーす
The answer is "None of the above"!
うん？
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
あんた タナベの えーっと…
Oh, you're, um... Tanabe's, uh...
リュシー･アスカムです
Lucie Ascam.
突然[とつぜん]:abrupt/sudden/unexpected
星野(ほしの)さん 突然だけど―
Hoshino-san, I know it's sudden, but
could I have a minute of your time?
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 頂ける[いただける]:to be able to receive|to be able to eat|to be acceptable
少しお時間 頂けますか？
（ハチマキ）えっ？
お… 俺に？
Who, me?
Yes.
はい ウフッ
ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
かっ！ あっ ま… まあ
ちょっとぐらいなら
W-Well, if it's just for
a minute, I guess so...
近接[きんせつ]:neighboring/neighbouring/adjacent, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track
（ハキム）
このISPV-７の近接軌道には―
We have detected no unusual changes
in the orbits adjacent to that of ISPV-7.
特別[とくべつ]:special, 変化[へんか]:change|variety|inflection|, 変化[へんげ]:shapeshifting (of an animal or spirit)|incarnation|transformation
特別な変化は見られません
検挙[けんきょ]:arrest/roundup, 不審[ふしん]:incomplete understanding/doubt/question, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 不法[ふほう]:lawlessness/injustice/illegality, 投棄[とうき]:abandonment/giving up/throwing away, 密輸[みつゆ]:smuggling/contraband trade, 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes
検挙した不審船も
不法投棄や密輸が中心で―
Also, the ships we've arrested are primarily
illegal dumpers and smugglers,
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 無関係[むかんけい]:unrelated, 推測[すいそく]:guess/conjecture
宇宙防衛戦線とは
無関係と推測されます
...and are presumably unrelated
to the Space Defense Front.
Understood.
（司令）分かった
We ask that all companies here continue using
Phase D for their communications net checks.
各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 通信網[つうしんもう]:communications network, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
（保安庁職員）
各企業の通信網チェックは―
引き続く[ひきつづく]:to continue (for a long time)/to occur in succession, フェーズ:phase, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
引き続き
フェーズＢでお願いします
Very well.
（ドルフ）分かりました
Given the strength of
its impact resistance,
副[ふく]:assistant|duplicate|adverb, 司令[しれい]:command/control/commander, 衝撃[しょうげき]:shock/impact/crash, 強度[きょうど]:strength/intensity, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（副司令１）
耐衝撃強度の問題からも―
セブン:seven, 標的[ひょうてき]:target, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
このセブンが
テロの標的となる可能性は―
...we believe that the likelihood of Seven
being a terrorist target is low.
低い[ひくい]:low (rank, degree, value, content, quality, etc.)|low (position)|short (height)|, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
低いと考えられます
うむ…
最も[もっとも, もとも]:most/extremely, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction
最も危険なのは
建造中のISPV-９か…
So it's ISPV-9 that's at the most risk,
since it's still under construction, huh?
いずれにせよ:at any rate/in any event/either way, テロリスト:terrorist, 脅迫[きょうはく]:threat/menace/coercion, 屈する[くっする]:to yield|to bend (knee, etc.)|to subdue|
いずれにせよ テロリストの脅迫に
屈するわけにはいかん
In any case, we mustn't
cave in to terrorist threats.
レーザー:laser/Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation, レーザー:leather, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, いくつ:how many?|how old?, 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||
うちのレーザー衛星を
いくつか回してやれ
Send over a few of our
laser satellites.
Yes, sir.
副[ふく]:assistant|duplicate|adverb, 司令[しれい]:command/control/commander
（副司令１）はい
What should we do about Seven's
environmental system maintenance?
副[ふく]:assistant|duplicate|adverb, 指令[しれい]:orders/instructions/directive, セブン:seven, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, システム:system, メンテナンス:maintenance
（副指令２）セブン内の
環境システムメンテナンスは―
どうしますか？
Let me think...
液化[えきか]:liquefaction, 純[じゅん]:innocent/chaste|pure, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 炭化[たんか]:carbonization/carbonisation, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
あっ そうか
液化純酸素炭化を使うし 問題だな
We'll be using liquid oxygen tankers...
That could be a problem.
Okay, let's move up
the schedule.
スケジュール:schedule, 繰り上げる[くりあげる]:to move up/to advance
よし スケジュールを繰り上げよう
各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 方々[かたがた]:they (of people)|you (usu. plural)|various, 方々[ほうぼう]:here and there/this way and that way/everywhere, 協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
各企業の方々にも
ご協力をお願いします
We request the assistance of
all businesses in this matter.
If this orbit can be protected,
Earth's safety is assured.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security
この軌道さえ守れば
地球は安全です
あっ
You're kidding me!
な… なんで？
んんん…
The M.O. Of the Space Defense Front
is to plant bombs in smoking rooms.
喫煙所[きつえんしょ, きつえんじょ]:smoking area (corner), 爆弾[ばくだん, バクダン]:bomb|alcohol with liquor added (esp. wine-based shochu highball, also beer with whiskey), 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps)
（業者）
喫煙所に爆弾を仕掛けるのが―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 手口[てぐち]:modus operandi/criminal technique/trick
宇宙防衛戦線の手口でね
地区[ちく]:district/section/sector, 喫煙[きつえん]:smoking, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 取り壊す[とりこわす]:to demolish/to tear or pull down, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
（業者）
だから この地区の喫煙所は
全部 取り壊すことになったんだ
So we've decided to tear down all
the smoking rooms in this sector.
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
（フィー）な… 全部！？
A-All of them?!
もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
言わせてもらうけどね
Pardon my saying so, but do you have any idea
how crazy it is to smoke in space?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|, 非常識[ひじょうしき]:lack of common sense/thoughtlessness/senselessness, 自覚[じかく]:self-consciousness/self-awareness
宇宙でタバコ吸うのが
どれだけ非常識か 自覚してる？
In this environment, air is the
most precious commodity we have.
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
この世界じゃ
空気が何より大事なもんなんだよ
And you deliberately foul it up?
- Just my luck, an anti-smoking activist...
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 嫌煙[けんえん]:dislike of smoking, 運動家[うんどうか]:activist/campaigner|athlete
（フィー）
しまった こいつ 嫌煙運動家だ
Do you know how much money it costs...
空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 浄化[じょうか]:purification/cleanup, いくら:how much?/how many?|even, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
（業者）空気を浄化するのに
いくらかかると思う？
...to purify the air you consume
in a single hour of smoking?
そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?"), 喫煙[きつえん]:smoking, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 設ける[もうける]:to prepare ahead of time|to create/to establish, 自体[じたい]:itself|one's own body|originally, 間違う[まちがう]:to make a mistake/to be incorrect/to be mistaken
そもそも 喫煙所を
設けたこと自体が間違ってたんだよ
It was a mistake to build these
smoking rooms in the first place.
税金[ぜいきん]:tax/duty, 無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness, 損害[そんがい]:damage/injury/loss
税金の無駄 損害だよ
It's a waste of tax money. A drain on resources.
今どき[いまどき]:these days/nowadays|at this time (of the day), 喫煙者[きつえんしゃ]:smoker, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 希少[きしょう]:scarce/rare, 動物[どうぶつ]:animal, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
今どきね 喫煙者なんてのは
希少動物みたいなもんだよ
These days, smokers are
an endangered species.
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 肺[はい]:lung, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 色[いろ]:colour|complexion|appearance||, 色[しょく]:counter for colours, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 想像[そうぞう]:imagination/guess
嫌だよね 自分の肺の中が
どんな色してるかなんて 想像…
It's revolting! I can't even imagine
what color your lungs are...
Why do I have to be lectured like that
when all I want is one little smoke?
一服[いっぷく]:(a) dose/(a) puff/(a) smoke
（フィー）なんで一服すんのに
ああまで言われなきゃならないんだ
Fine, I'll admit that I'm a
little ashamed of the habit.
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is, 確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, 引ける[ひける]:to close/to be over|to lose one's nerve
そりゃ 確かに
ちょっとばかり気は引けるけどさ
Even so, I can't believe they're
tearing down all of them...
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 取り壊す[とりこわす]:to demolish/to tear or pull down
それにしたって
全部 取り壊さなくたって―
対処[たいしょ]:dealing with/coping with, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, いくら:how much?/how many?|even
対処の方法はいくらでも…
There's a ton of other ways
that they could've dealt with...
うん？
イヒッ…
うん ん… うん？
ん… うん？
Open Flames Prohibited
ん！？
It looks wonderful
on you.
似合い[にあい]:well-matched/becoming/suitable
（店員）よくお似合いですよ
Senpai would laugh at me
if he saw me in this.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
（タナベ）先輩 見たら笑うな
Your boyfriend would love to see you
in something this mature.
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, っぽい:-ish/-like|tossing something out, なさる:to do
（店員）このくらい
大人っぽくなさったほうが―
喜ぶ[よろこぶ]:to be delighted|to congratulate|to gratefully accept
彼も喜びますよ
えっ… 彼？
Huh? Boyfriend?
Oh, Cheng-Shin-san isn't my...
い… いえ
チェンシンさんは そんなんじゃ…
If I wore that, I'd look
too enthusiastic.
気合い[きあい]:scream/yell/fighting spirit, 過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much)
あれじゃ 気合い入り過ぎだよね
デート:date/go on a date
デートとかいうんじゃなくて―
This isn't a date, we're just
getting together for dinner.
食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat
ただ 会って
食事するだけなんだし… ん？
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩！
Senpai!
Welcome.
いらっしゃる:to come/to go|is (doing)
（店員）いらっしゃいませ
Oh, um, I'm meeting someone.
I'm meeting someone.
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ..., 待ち合わせ[まちあわせ]:appointment
（タナベ）あっ えーっと
待ち合わせ… 待ち合わせなんで
I realize that this is sudden
and it might surprise you,
突然[とつぜん]:abrupt/sudden/unexpected, 驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished
（リュシー）
突然で驚いたと思いますけど―
...but you aren't
seeing anyone, right?
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
つきあってる人
いないんでしょう？
Huh? No.
（ハチマキ）あ… ああ
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（リュシー）だったら お願い
結婚してなんて言わないわ
Then please do me this favor.
I'm not
asking you to get married or anything.
星野さんの彼女に
してくれるだけでいいの
Just being your girlfriend
is enough!
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please
いいっ！？
（リュシー）お願い 星野さん
Please, Hoshino-san!
（ハチマキ）あっ ああ…
T-That doesn't make
any sense at all!
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely
ぜ… 全然 分からん！
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other, いかん:Italian warship, いかん:ancient headgear showing rank
どうして 俺がタナベと
つきあわな いかんのだ
Why do I have to get Tanabe
to be my girlfriend?!
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
（リュシー）
私は チェンシンさんが好きなの
I'm in love with Cheng-Shin-san!
（ハチマキ）はあ？
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
（リュシー）
だから タナベとチェンシンさんが
つきあうのは困るの
So I don't want Cheng-Shin-san and
Tanabe to go out, understand?
分かる？
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
（ハチマキ）そんな理由で
俺の彼女を決めんなよ
Don't saddle me with a girlfriend
over something like that, okay?
That's not the only reason
that I'm asking you.
別に それだけで
言ってるわけじゃないわよ
（ハチマキ）お？
Don't you see? Tanabe has a thing
for you, Hoshino-san.
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
いい？ タナベはね
星野さんが好きなの
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
いい？ タナベはね
星野さんが好きなの
いっ！
口[くち]:mouth|opening|mouth (of a bottle)||, 口[く, こう]:mouth/speech|counter for people or implements, 鋭い[するどい]:sharp (blade)|sharp (pain)|perceptive|
口には出さないけど
私そういうのは鋭いんだから
She hasn't said as much, but I pick up
on these things really quickly!
口[くち]:mouth|opening|mouth (of a bottle)||, 口[く, こう]:mouth/speech|counter for people or implements, 鋭い[するどい]:sharp (blade)|sharp (pain)|perceptive|
口には出さないけど
私そういうのは鋭いんだから
こういうときはね―
At times like this, the boy
has to pick up on the signs!
男の子[おとこのこ, おとこのコ]:boy/male child/baby boy, 男の子[おのこ]:man/boy, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
男の子のほうから
気付いてあげなくちゃ
男の子[おとこのこ, おとこのコ]:boy/male child/baby boy, 男の子[おのこ]:man/boy, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
男の子のほうから
気付いてあげなくちゃ
あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
あああ…
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|
女の子に言わせるなんて
最低だからね
あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
あああ…
There's nothing worse than making
the girl spell it out for him!
分かってる？
Understand?!
あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
（ハチマキ）あああ…
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
お願い タナベのこと
しっかり捕まえててやって
Please, I'm begging you.
Hold on tight to Tanabe, okay?
（ハチマキ）あ… ああっ ケッ！
いらっしゃる:to come/to go|is (doing)
（店員）いらっしゃいませ
Hello, miss.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
あの… さっきのやつください！
That dress I tried on! Ring it up!
修理[しゅうり, しゅり]:repairing/mending/servicing, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
（ユーリ）はい
修理は間もなく終わりますので―
Right. Repairs are almost completed,
so we'll be leaving port on schedule.
出航[しゅっこう]:departure/sailing/shipping out, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly
出航は予定どおりに―
We will rendezvous with the tug ship in
circumlunar orbit, and our ETA at Seven...
周回[しゅうかい]:going around/orbiting|circumference, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, ランデブー:meeting/rendez-vous
月周回軌道で
タグシップとランデブーし―
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
４日後の16時に…
...is four days from now at 1600 hours.
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
（ラビィ）
タバコ 吸いに行ったんだよな？
- I thought you went out for a smoke.
I copy.
Because of the maintenance work being
done on Seven's environmental systems,
（フィー）んんっ…
...please berth
in Bay Five.
I copy.
バギー:buggy/stroller, 鍵[かぎ, カギ]:key|lock, 鍵[けん]:key (of a piano, etc.), 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
バギーの鍵 借りるわね
I'm borrowing the keys
to the buggy.
Fee-kun? Where are
you going?
フィー:phi
（ラビィ）フィー君 どこ行くの？
Hey!
ねえ
Fee-kun, what's going on?
フィー:phi, 何事[なにごと]:what|nothing (with neg. verb)|something or other
（ラビィ）フィー君 何事だい？
Cigarettes!
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret
タバコ
（ラビィ）はっ？
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|, 隣[となり]:neighbor (neighbour)/next to (esp. living next door to), 工業都市[こうぎょうとし]:industrial (manufacturing, factory) town or city
（フィー）タバコ 吸ってくる
隣の工業都市まで
I'm gonna go have a smoke.
In the next tunnel city over.
Fee-san, our final maintenance check
will be complete in one hour.
フィー:phi
（ユーリ）フィーさん
最終[さいしゅう]:last/final/closing, メンテナンス:maintenance, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
あと１時間で
最終メンテナンス 終わりますよ
I'll be back in 30 minutes!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（フィー）30分で戻る
You're Toy Box's captain, aren't you?!
This is an order from your superior!
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
君は ToyBoxの船長だろ！
上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
上司命令だ！ 今すぐ戻って…
Come back here
immediately!
（フィー）んんんん…
…こなくていいです
Or not, it's up to you.
Have a pleasant trip, ma'am.
いってらっしゃいませ
（フィー）ハァ よし！
Right!
あっ… あれ？
Seems kind of contradictory to have
a smoke when you're in high spirits...
張り切る[はりきる]:to be in high spirits/to be full of vigor (vigour)/to be enthusiastic, 一服[いっぷく]:(a) dose/(a) puff/(a) smoke, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 矛盾[むじゅん]:contradiction/inconsistency
張り切って一服するってのも
なんか矛盾してる
張り切る[はりきる]:to be in high spirits/to be full of vigor (vigour)/to be enthusiastic, 一服[いっぷく]:(a) dose/(a) puff/(a) smoke, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 矛盾[むじゅん]:contradiction/inconsistency
張り切って一服するってのも
なんか矛盾してる
ん？
あんた…
Hey, you're...
ぬうっ…
フッ…
互い[たがい]:mutual/reciprocal, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
お互い 頑張りましょう
Keep the faith, brother. Let's hang in there.
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
し… 失礼 急いでるもんで
E-Excuse me, I'm in a hurry.
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
急いでる？
In a hurry?
Then what were you having a smoke for?
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
タバコ 吸ってたくせに
ん？
忘れ物[わすれもの]:lost article/something forgotten
ちょっと 忘れ物
Hey, buddy! You forgot something!
Hey!
おーい:hey!/oi!|I
おーい
あっ…
喫煙室[きつえんしつ]:smoking room/smoking compartment, 爆弾[ばくだん, バクダン]:bomb|alcohol with liquor added (esp. wine-based shochu highball, also beer with whiskey), 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), おはこ:one's favourite party trick (favorite)/one's specialty|No. 18
（作業員）やつら 喫煙室に
爆弾 仕掛けるのが おはこだから
Their favorite stunt lately is planting bombs
in smoking rooms.
ん？
やっぱり:too/also|still
や… やっぱり！
I should've known!
（男性）うわあっ
（女性）ああっ
（フィー）うっ…
ハァ… ヒヒッ…
Nothing over here! How about you?
Call the police!
おーい:hey!/oi!|I
（男性）おーい 誰かいるか？
Hey! Is anybody here?!
Shut off the water!
あっ あんた
Hey, are you...
Hey, we've got a survivor
over here!
おーい:hey!/oi!|I, 生存者[せいぞんしゃ, せいざんしゃ]:survivor
おーい 生存者だ
おい 大丈夫か？ あんた なあ
Hey, are you okay? Say something!
（フィー）うっ…
フフフフ… フフフ…
（男性）あの…
Um...
This is a reminder that open flames are strictly
prohibited in all pressurized sectors.
油圧[ゆあつ]:oil pressure/hydraulics, 区画[くかく]:division/section/compartment, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within
（アナウンス）油圧区画内での―
火気[かき, かっき]:fire, 取り扱い[とりあつかい]:treatment/service/handling, 全面[ぜんめん]:whole surface/entire, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, 注意[ちゅうい]:caution/being careful/attention (heed), 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
火気取り扱い全面禁止についての
注意連絡です
現在[げんざい]:now/current/present
現在 ISPV-７の…
ISPV-7 is currently undergoing
a thorough ECLS inspection,
...particularly oxygen
supply systems.
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 供給[きょうきゅう]:supply/provision, 部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part, 総[そう]:whole/all/general, 総[ふさ]:tuft|bunch (of grapes, etc.)|section (of an orange, etc.), 点検[てんけん]:inspection/examination/checking
特に 酸素供給部分についての
総点検を…
ほんと:truth/reality|proper
（キース）ええっ？ ほんとかよ
What, seriously?
Toy Box is back? She's ahead of schedule.
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（キース）ToyBoxが帰ってきた？
予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
予定より 早いなあ
おかえり:return|welcome home, うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（キース）おかえりな… うわあ
Welcome ba...
（リュシー）チェンシンさん
Cheng-Shin-san!
ん？
Lucie, take a look
at this.
（社員）リュシー これ見ろよ
Come on, cut it out.
（チェンシン）おい よせよ
He says he was on
a date yesterday.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, デート:date/go on a date
（社員）
昨日 デートだったんだってよ
She's some new girl in Half Section, apparently.
Do you know her, Lucie?
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
半課の新人らしいけど
リュシー 知ってる？
Oh, I know her
really well.
よーく 知ってます
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
友達ですから 私の
She's my friend,
after all.
So, how'd it go?
（ハチマキ）
…で どうだったんだよ
（タナベ）何がですか？
How did what go?
デート:date/go on a date
（ハチマキ）
チェンシンとのデートだよ
Your date with Cheng-Shin.
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun
（タナベ）とても楽しかったです
I had a great time.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
先輩こそ
リュシーとつきあうんですか？
How about you, Senpai?
Are you and Lucie an item?
（ハチマキ）ぐっ… はあ？
告白[こくはく]:confession|profession of love|confession of sins (e.g. the confessional), 喫茶店[きっさてん, きっちゃてん]:coffee shop/tearoom/coffee lounge
（タナベ）
告白されたんでしょ？ 喫茶店で
She spilled her guts to you
in that coffee shop, right?
ええっ！？ うう… ああ…
まいる:to go/to come|to be defeated
ハッハー いや まいったね
見てる女は見てるんだよなあ
Hey, what's a guy to do? Girls with an
eye for quality know where to look.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, フリー:free (of restraint, controls, etc.)
まっ 今はちょうどフリーだし―
I'm on the market right now, so I guess I
can go out with her every once in a while.
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, デート:date/go on a date, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
たまには
デートくらいしてやってもいいかな
Try not to get dumped
this time, okay?
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）今度は
フラれないようにしてくださいね
くっ…
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
（フィー）よーし 吸うぞ
Yeah, it's smokin' time!
I'm gonna smoke 'til I'm blue in the face!
吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|, まくる:to turn up/to roll up (e.g. sleeves)|to do relentlessly
吸いまくってやる
I swear, I can't figure out
Cheng-Shin's taste in women.
趣味[しゅみ]:hobby/pastime|tastes, あきれる:to be amazed/to be shocked/to be astonished
しっかし チェンシンの
女の趣味には あきれるね
It must be like how gourmet eaters
like to eat really weird stuff.
まっ あれだな
グルメ:fine food/high-quality food, ゲテモノ:low-quality products/strange thing/strange combination, 料理[りょうり]:cooking/cookery|dealing with something, 手を出す[てをだす]:to turn one's hand to|to get involved in|to start a fight
グルメが ゲテモノ料理に
手を出すようなもんだな
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）チェンシンさんのこと
悪く言わないでください！
Don't you dare badmouth Cheng-Shin-san!
What's with you? You think you're
Mrs. Cheng-Shin already?!
女房[にょうぼう, にょうぼ]:wife (esp. one's own wife)|court lady|woman (esp. as a love interest), 気取り[きどり]:affectation/pretension
（ハチマキ）何だよ！
もう チェンシンの女房気取りかよ
吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily
（フィー）吸うぞ 必ず 今すぐに
Smoke. Definitely smoke. Smoke soon.
そんなこと言ってるから
クレアさんにもフラれるんですよ！
Claire-san dumped you because
you say mean things like that!
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
くっ…
クレアは関係ねえだろ… んぐ
Claire's got nothing
to do with this!
ゲテモノ:low-quality products/strange thing/strange combination, いっちょまえ:becoming an adult or full-fledged member of (a) society
ゲテモノが いっちょまえの… んん
Freak food, order up!
（フィー）アハハハ…
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（課長）やめてー！
Stop it, please!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめてよ ２人とも
Stop it, you two!
（ハチマキ）お前なんかな―
Go get yourself knocked up
and head back down to Earth!
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away, つくる:to make/to produce|to prepare (food), 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
とっととガキでもつくって
地球(オカ)に帰りやがれー！
（ハチマキ）あっ…
（タナベ）ああっ
It's smokin' time!
吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
吸うぞー！
あ…
Um, we didn't mean to...
（タナベ）あの… これは
My smoker's seat...
シート:seat
（フィー）
私のスモーカーズシート…
（ハチマキ）
ユーリまで来なくってもさ―
You didn't have to come out, too, Yuri.
One Fishbone is enough to do the job.
台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx, 平気[へいき]:coolness/calmness|all right
あれ１つなら １台でも平気なのに
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（ユーリ）頼みますよ
Please, I have to. I can't stay on board
Toy Box with Fee-san like that.
フィー:phi, っきり:only/just|since, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
あのフィーさんと２人っきりで
ToyBoxに残るなんて
Yeah, you have a point...
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
（ハチマキ）そりゃ そっか
禁煙[きんえん]:abstaining from smoking/quitting smoking|No Smoking!
（ユーリ）
ToyBoxは禁煙ですからね
Toy Box is a smoke-free ship.
She hasn't had a cigarette in over ten days.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|
これでもう
10日以上 吸っていないことに
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, つらい:painful/bitter|tough
（ハチマキ）
ああ 確かにつらいかもな
It must be rough
for her.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（タナベ）
悪いことしちゃいましたね
We really messed up,
didn't we?
（ユーリ）
まあ あと ２時間ほどで―
Well, they say that they will have her smoker's
seat repaired in another two hours or so,
シート:seat, 直る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended
スモーカーズシートも
直るそうですから―
...so by the time we finish this job
and return to Seven, it will...
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, セブン:seven, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
この仕事が終わって
セブンに戻れば…
あ…
電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things
（ハチマキ）どうした？ ユーリ
（ユーリ）電波です
What's up, Yuri?
A signal. That debris
is relaying a video feed.
デブリ:debris, 映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 中継[ちゅうけい]:relay/hook-up|relay broadcasting, 中継[なかつぎ]:joining/joint|mid-relief pitcher, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
あのデブリ 映像を中継しています
You mean
it's still active?
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
生きてるってことですか？
Fee? Fee, do you
read me?
フィー:phi, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（ハチマキ）
フィー フィー 聞こえてるか？
フィー:phi, ねえさん:elder sister|(vocative) young lady
（ハチマキ）ぐっ… あの…
いいかな？ フィーねえさん
Um, do you have a moment,
nice and wonderful Fee-san?
フィー:phi, ねえさん:elder sister|(vocative) young lady
（ハチマキ）ぐっ… あの…
いいかな？ フィーねえさん
デブリ:debris, 電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
あのデブリ 電波 出してる
みたいなんだけど―
That debris seems to be
sending out a signal,
but we can't get any details on it from here.
詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
こっちじゃ
詳しいこと 分かんないし
確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
（ユーリ）ToyBoxで
確認してもらえませんか？
Could we trouble you to get
verification with Toy Box?
今… 今 見てる
I'm... I'm watching it now.
Attention, those who possess rights
and interests in outer space
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 権益[けんえき]:(one's) interests, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 諸君[しょくん]:you (people)|gentlemen/ladies and gentlemen
（コートの男）
宇宙空間に権益を持つ諸君
This message is directed at
each and every one of you.
メッセージ:message, 一人一人[ひとりひとり, ひとりびとり]:one by one/each/one at a time, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
このメッセージは
君たち一人一人に送るものだ
声明[せいめい]:declaration/statement/proclamation, 声明[しょうみょう]:sabdavidya (ancient Indian linguistic and grammatical studies)|chanting of Buddhist hymns (usu. in Sanskrit or Chinese), とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), 一連[いちれん]:series|two reams (i.e. 1000 sheets of paper)|verse, 爆破[ばくは]:destructive blast/blowing up/explosion, 警告[けいこく]:warning/advice, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
（コートの男）声明にあったとおり
月での一連の爆破は警告にすぎない
As stated in our claim
of responsibility,
...the string of bombings on the
moon are merely a warning.
声明[せいめい]:declaration/statement/proclamation, 声明[しょうみょう]:sabdavidya (ancient Indian linguistic and grammatical studies)|chanting of Buddhist hymns (usu. in Sanskrit or Chinese), とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), 一連[いちれん]:series|two reams (i.e. 1000 sheets of paper)|verse, 爆破[ばくは]:destructive blast/blowing up/explosion, 警告[けいこく]:warning/advice, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
（コートの男）声明にあったとおり
月での一連の爆破は警告にすぎない
They've hacked into
our channel!
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 回線[かいせん]:circuit/line, 強制[きょうせい]:obligation/coercion/compulsion, 介入[かいにゅう]:intervention
（男性１）
回線に強制介入されました
世紀末[せいきまつ]:end of a century (esp. 19th)/fin-de-siècle, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 資源[しげん]:resources, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（コートの男）
20世紀末 石油資源は
有限だと気付いた人類は―
When humanity realized at the
end of the 20th Century...
世紀末[せいきまつ]:end of a century (esp. 19th)/fin-de-siècle, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 資源[しげん]:resources, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（コートの男）
20世紀末 石油資源は
有限だと気付いた人類は―
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 発信[はっしん]:dispatch/despatch/transmission, 源[みなもと]:source (of a river)/fountainhead|source, 源[げん]:source/origin, 特定[とくてい]:specific/particular|specifying, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
（男性２）
発信源 特定を急げ！
Pinpoint the transmission source! Hurry!
...that Earth's oil resources
were limited,
Contact the news center!
世紀末[せいきまつ]:end of a century (esp. 19th)/fin-de-siècle, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 資源[しげん]:resources, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（コートの男）
20世紀末 石油資源は
有限だと気付いた人類は―
世紀末[せいきまつ]:end of a century (esp. 19th)/fin-de-siècle, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 資源[しげん]:resources, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（コートの男）
20世紀末 石油資源は
有限だと気付いた人類は―
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 報道[ほうどう]:information/report|to report, センター:centre/center
（男性３）
報道センターに―
世紀末[せいきまつ]:end of a century (esp. 19th)/fin-de-siècle, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 資源[しげん]:resources, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（コートの男）
20世紀末 石油資源は
有限だと気付いた人類は―
世紀末[せいきまつ]:end of a century (esp. 19th)/fin-de-siècle, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 資源[しげん]:resources, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（コートの男）
20世紀末 石油資源は
有限だと気付いた人類は―
連絡を取る[れんらくをとる]:to get in touch with
連絡を取れ！
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, エネルギー:energy, 求める[もとめる]:to want|to request|to seek|, 試行錯誤[しこうさくご]:trial and error, 奪い合い[うばいあい]:scramble (for), 明け暮れる[あけくれる]:to do nothing but/to spend all one's time doing
新しいエネルギーを求めての
試行錯誤と 奪い合いに明け暮れた
...there was much trial and error as they
scrambled to find a new source of energy.
Get confirmation with
the OSA! Hurry!
保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954), 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
保安庁への確認 急げ！
太陽光発電[たいようこうはつでん]:solar power (generation), 天然[てんねん]:nature/spontaneity|natural airhead, ウラン:uranium (U)
太陽光発電 天然ガス ウラン
Solar power. Natural gas. Uranium.
Methane hydrate from the ocean floor.
海底[かいてい, うなぞこ]:bottom of the ocean|undersea/submarine, メタン:methane
海底メタンハイドレート
そして 月だ
And then... the moon!
These terrorists
have some nerve!
テロリスト:terrorist, 堂々[どうどう]:magnificent|fair|grandly|
テロリストが堂々と！？
Humanity obtained the moon's helium-3,
and it seemed as if the problem were solved.
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, ヘリウム:helium (He), 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
（コートの男）人類は
月のヘリウム３を手に入れて―
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 解決[かいけつ]:settlement/solution/resolution, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
問題は解決したかに見えた
In fact, over 70% of the world's current
energy needs are met with helium-3.
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality), 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 電力[でんりょく]:electric power, 需要[じゅよう]:demand/request, パーセント:percent/percentage, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
実際 今や世界の電力需要の
70パーセント以上が―
ヘリウム:helium (He), 賄う[まかなう]:to give board to/to provide meals/to pay
ヘリウム３によって賄われている
だが どうだ
But what of it? The fact of the matter is that
we have merely substituted helium-3 for oil.
実態[じったい]:true state/actual condition/reality, 石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, ヘリウム:helium (He), 移る[うつる]:to move (house)|to change the target of interest or concern|to elapse (passage of time)||
実態は 石油からヘリウム３に
移っただけのことだ
文明[ぶんめい]:civilization/civilisation|Bummei era (1469.4.28-1487.7.20), 発達[はったつ]:development/growth, 引き換え[ひきかえ]:exchange/conversion, 有限[ゆうげん]:finite/limited, エネルギー:energy, 食い荒らす[くいあらす]:to eat up and spoil (e.g. crops)|to eat a bit of everything|to encroach upon
文明の発達と引き換えに
有限なエネルギーを食い荒らす
There has been no change
whatsoever in human nature,
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 性質[せいしつ]:nature/property/disposition, 変わり[かわり]:change|unusual state or event|difference
人類の性質に
何ら変わりはなかった
...which is willing to fuel the growth of our
civilization by devouring a limited resource.
Humanity has learned nothing from
the mistakes of the last century!
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 世紀[せいき]:century/era, 過ち[あやまち]:fault/error/indiscretion, 学ぶ[まなぶ]:to study (in depth)/to learn/to take lessons in
人類は 前世紀の過ちに
何も学ばなかったのだ
What's he mean?
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 世紀[せいき]:century/era, 過ち[あやまち]:fault/error/indiscretion, 学ぶ[まなぶ]:to study (in depth)/to learn/to take lessons in
人類は 前世紀の過ちに
何も学ばなかったのだ
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（課長）
これってどういうこと？
我々[われわれ]:we, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 声[こえ]:voice, 星々[ほしぼし]:stars/the stars and planets/celestial bodies, 代弁者[だいべんしゃ]:spokesman/mouthpiece
我々 宇宙防衛戦線は
声なき星々の代弁者だ
That we shouldn't
mess up space, I guess.
We of the Space Defense Front speak
for that which has no voice, the stars.
我々[われわれ]:we, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 声[こえ]:voice, 星々[ほしぼし]:stars/the stars and planets/celestial bodies, 代弁者[だいべんしゃ]:spokesman/mouthpiece
我々 宇宙防衛戦線は
声なき星々の代弁者だ
要する[ようする]:to need/to demand/to take
（ラビィ）要するに―
我々[われわれ]:we, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 声[こえ]:voice, 星々[ほしぼし]:stars/the stars and planets/celestial bodies, 代弁者[だいべんしゃ]:spokesman/mouthpiece
我々 宇宙防衛戦線は
声なき星々の代弁者だ
我々[われわれ]:we, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 声[こえ]:voice, 星々[ほしぼし]:stars/the stars and planets/celestial bodies, 代弁者[だいべんしゃ]:spokesman/mouthpiece
我々 宇宙防衛戦線は
声なき星々の代弁者だ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 荒らす[あらす]:to lay waste|to invade|to troll (e.g. web forums)
宇宙を荒らすなって
ことでは？
我々[われわれ]:we, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 声[こえ]:voice, 星々[ほしぼし]:stars/the stars and planets/celestial bodies, 代弁者[だいべんしゃ]:spokesman/mouthpiece
我々 宇宙防衛戦線は
声なき星々の代弁者だ
覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
覚悟せよ 今日こそは―
Prepare yourselves!
For today will be remembered as the day
that humanity withdrew from the heavens!
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 撤退[てったい]:evacuation/withdrawal/revocation, 記念日[きねんび]:holiday/anniversary/memorial day
人類が宇宙空間から撤退する
記念日となるだろう
ああ？
Huh? That's not debris... It's...
デブリ:debris
あれ デブリじゃ… あれ？
Now I get it. They're at it again...
（フィー）そうか またこいつらか
Okay, if that's how
you want it!
上等[じょうとう]:superior/first-class|(that's) just fine!
上等だよ！
エンジン:engine
（ハチマキ）な… 何だ？ あれ
エンジンが３つもついてるぞ
W-What the hell is that?
It's got three engines on it!
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite
（タナベ）通信衛星じゃ？
It can't be a communications
satellite, can it?
追いかける[おいかける]:to chase/to run after/to pursue
（ハチマキ）
追いかけたほうがいいのかな
Maybe we should
chase after it.
テロリスト:terrorist, 細工[さいく]:work/craftsmanship/tactics, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods
（ユーリ）でも
テロリストが細工した物ですから
Perhaps, but it is something that
the terrorists put together, so...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track
あっ まさか この軌道は…
Oh, no! This trajectory, it...
セブン:seven, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
セブンに向かってる！？
It's headed
for Seven?!
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
（タナベ）
う… うちの会社ですか？
F-For our company?!
ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
（ユーリ）
うちだけではありませんよ
No, not just ours!
（ハチマキ）
ど… どうすんだよ おい
What should we do?!
（タナベ）
そんなこと私に言われても…
Don't ask me! Yuri-san?
- If they keep this up...
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
（フィー）これ以上…
これ以上 私の邪魔をすると…
Anyway, we should contact the OSA.
- If they keep getting between me and my cigs...
えっ？ あっ…
...l'M GONNA LOSE IT!
キレる:to get angry/to snap/to blow one's top
キレちゃうぞ！
自動[じどう]:automatic/self-motion|intransitive verb, 運転[うんてん]:operation (of a machine, etc.)|driving|working (capital, etc.)
（ハチマキ）だあっ 自動運転に！
It switched
to autopilot!
フィー:phi
お… おい フィー！
Hey! Fee!
ざけんな！
Don't screw with me!
シート:seat, 直る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended, 貴様[きさま]:you/you bastard|you
もうすぐ スモーカーズシートが
直るってのに それを貴様ら
My smoker's seat is almost fixed,
and now you bastards want to...
Bogey has stopped
accelerating!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 加速[かそく]:acceleration/speeding up, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person
（管制官１）
正体不明機 加速を停止しました
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 相対[あいたい]:confrontation/facing/between ourselves, 相対[そうたい]:relativity|relative, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate
（管制官２）相対速度
6,14キロメートルパーセコンド
Relative velocity, 6.14km per second!
やはり:too/also|still, 我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, ステーション:station, 交差[こうさ]:crossing/intersection|(genetic) crossing over, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 接触[せっしょく]:touch/contact, 恐れる[おそれる]:to fear/to be afraid of
やはり 我がステーションとの
交差軌道上です 接触の恐れあり
It's on an intercept orbit with this station,
all right! There's a risk of collision!
ナイン:nine, 標的[ひょうてき]:target, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
ああっ ナインではなく
こっちが標的だったなんて
I can't believe that we were
their target, not Nine...
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 暫定[ざんてい]:tentative/temporary, コース:course (route, trail, course of study, course of action, plan, option)
（管制官３）暫定コース 出ました
We have a tentative course projection!
Impact in seven minutes!
衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict
衝突まで あと７分！
Commander!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 司令[しれい]:command/control/commander
（管制官３）司令！
うろたえる:to be flustered/to lose one's presence of mind
うろたえるな！
Calm down! Seven can withstand an impact
with a satellite of that size.
程度[ていど]:degree/amount/grade, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, セブン:seven, 耐える[たえる]:to bear|to support|to be fit for
あの程度の衛星
このセブンなら耐えられる
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, セブン:seven, 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, メンテ:maintenance
しかし
我がセブンは 環境メンテ中です
But Seven is undergoing
environmental maintenance, sir.
ああ？
Our oxygen pressurization
is at level red.
副[ふく]:assistant|duplicate|adverb, 司令[しれい]:command/control/commander, ステーション:station, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), レベル:level/standard/amount, レッド:red
（副司令２）ステーション内の
酸素分圧は レベルレッドです
If we're hit by debris in this state, the impact will
cause Seven to catch fire and blow to pieces!
状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, デブリ:debris, 衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict
この状態で
デブリが衝突すれば―
セブン:seven, 衝撃[しょうげき]:shock/impact/crash, 引火[いんか]:ignition/catching fire, 爆散[ばくさん]:bursting and scattering/popping and being dispersed
セブンは衝撃で引火 爆散します
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
駄目です
ユーリさんと離れ過ぎちゃって
It's no use, we're too
far away from Yuri-san.
Now I get it. They're going
for the Kessler Syndrome.
狙い[ねらい]:aim, シンドローム:syndrome
（ハチマキ）
そうか やつらの狙いは
ケスラー･シンドロームだ
What's that?
（タナベ）何ですか？ それ
It means that debris
creates debris.
デブリ:debris, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
デブリがデブリを
作っちまうことだよ
When debris collides with an artificial celestial
body, parts break off somewhere, right?
デブリ:debris, 衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict, 人工[じんこう]:artificial/man-made/human work, 天体[てんたい]:heavenly body/celestial body/astronomical object
デブリと衝突した人工天体は
どっか ぶっ壊れちまうだろ？
When that happens, those fragments slam
into another object, creating even more.
破片[はへん]:fragment/broken piece/splinter, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter
すると その破片が
また別の物にぶつかって―
どんどん:drumming (noise)|rapidly/steadily, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply
どんどん増えていくんだ
たった:only/merely/but, デブリ:debris, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 億[おく]:10^8/100,000,000/hundred million, 生む[うむ]:to give birth/to bear (child)|to produce
たった１つのデブリが
数億のデブリを生むことだってある
A single piece of debris can
generate billions of pieces.
So what would happen if something
as big as Seven breaks up?
セブン:seven, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, ブレイク:break (rest), アップ:increasing
（タナベ）じゃあ セブンみたいな
大きな物がブレイクアップしたら…
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, デブリ:debris, 包む[つつむ]:to wrap up/to tuck in|to conceal, 包む[くるむ]:to wrap up/to tuck in/to pack
（ハチマキ）
地球はデブリに包まれて―
The Earth would be surrounded by debris,
and it'd be completely cut off from space.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 断絶[だんぜつ]:extinction|severance|to become extinct|
宇宙と完全に断絶する！
（タナベ）うそ…
No way!
The bogey is accelerating randomly!
They can't keep a lock!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 乱数[らんすう]:random number, 加速[かそく]:acceleration/speeding up, 捉える[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
（管制官１）正体不明機
乱数加速で捉えきれません
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 中央[ちゅうおう]:centre/center|metropolis, レーザー:laser/Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation, レーザー:leather, 射程[しゃてい]:range (e.g. of a rifle, missile, etc.), 圏[けん]:sphere/circle|category (only in the context of "category theory"), 突破[とっぱ]:breaking through/breakthrough/penetration
（管制官２）
中央レーザー射程圏 突破されます
It's broken through our
central lasers' zone of fire!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), リチャージ:recharge, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
（管制官３）
リチャージまで あと 140秒
140 seconds
until recharge!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
（管制官４）衝突まで 120秒
120 seconds
to impact!
Get the civilian ships evacuated!
They get top priority!
What are our portside
lasers doing?!
左舷[さげん]:port (left side of vessel), レーザー:laser/Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation, レーザー:leather
左舷レーザーは何をしている
ナイン:nine, 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||
あっ… ナインに回したのか？
Right, I sent them
to Nine...
It's still heading
for Seven!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
宇宙防衛戦線のバカどもが！
You Space Defense Front
sons of bitches!
半径[はんけい]:radius, タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 吸う[すう]:to smoke|to suck|to absorb|, あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
半径400キロで タバコが吸えるのは
あそこだけなんだよ！
That's the only place in a 400km radius
where I can smoke!
ミサイル:missile
ミサイルはどうした
Where are
those missiles?!
既に[すでに, すんでに]:already/too late, 基[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 基[き]:group|(free) radical|counter for installed or mounted objects (e.g. stone lanterns, gravestones, satellites), 迎撃[げいげき]:intercept/interception/counter attack, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
（管制官）既に３基が
迎撃に向かってます
Three missiles are already en route
to intercept! 152 seconds to target!
目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
目標まで 152秒
衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
（司令）何を言ってる
衝突まで 100秒だぞ！
What're you saying?
Impact is in 100 seconds!
セブン:seven, ブレイク:break (rest), アップ:increasing
（ハチマキ）
セブンがブレイクアップしたら―
If Seven breaks up, this area's gonna
be crawling with debris, too.
辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, デブリ:debris, だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood)
この辺りもデブリだらけになる
救助[きゅうじょ]:relief/aid/rescue, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
お前は
こいつに入って救助を受けろ
Climb into this
and wait for rescue!
But what about you, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）先輩はどうするんです？
高度[こうど]:altitude/height|high-degree, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, やり過ごす[やりすごす]:to let something (or somebody) go past|to do too much
（ハチマキ）
高度を取ってやり過ごす
Gain some altitude
and slip past it.
That's crazy! You'd never be able
to climb high enough in time!
ムチャですよ
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
今からじゃ
とても上がりきれませんよ
If you die, it'll break Cheng-Shin's heart, got it?
泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob
お前が死んだら
チェンシンが泣くだろ！
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 悲しむ[かなしむ]:to be sad/to mourn for/to regret
（タナベ）先輩だって
リュシーを悲しませないで！
Don't make Lucie cry
over you, too, okay?
な…
近接[きんせつ]:neighboring/neighbouring/adjacent, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 退避[たいひ]:taking refuge/evacuation|saving (a file), くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（クレア）DS-12
近接軌道から緊急退避してください
DS-12, you're on an adjacent orbit! Please get clear!
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, 救助[きゅうじょ]:relief/aid/rescue, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing
DS-12 聞こえますか？
救助作業を…
DS-12, do you read?
Stand by for rescue operations!
手入れ[ていれ]:care/looking after|(police) raid, ばっか:only/merely|approximately
手入れしたばっかで これか！
We just got her fixed,
and now this?!
Is this station a damned giant tortoise?!
You have 70 seconds to alter our orientation!
ステーション:station, ゾウガメ:giant tortoise
（司令）
このステーションは ゾウガメか！
秒[びょう]:second (60th min), 姿勢[しせい]:attitude/posture/stance, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration
70秒で姿勢変更だ！
- It's impossible!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min), 回避[かいひ]:evasion/avoidance, 不可能[ふかのう]:impossible
（管制官１）無理です
（管制官２）あと50秒 回避不可能
Impact in 50! Evasion impossible!
She asked me
to do her a favor!
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（ハチマキ）
頼まれたんだよ あれは
（タナベ）何をですか？
To do what?!
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
（ハチマキ）
お前をしっかり捕まえておけってな
To hold on tight
to you!
えっ？
うっ… ああ…
The mass catcher won't
deploy in time!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
（管制官１）
マスキャッチャー 間に合いません
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 秒[びょう]:second (60th min), 衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict
（管制官２）
あと30秒 衝突します！
30 seconds to impact!
It's going to hit!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 衝撃[しょうげき]:shock/impact/crash, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|
（管制官３）衝撃に備えろ！
Brace for impact!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目か
So, we couldn't stop it...
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 突っ込む[つっこむ]:to thrust (something) into (something)|to plunge into|to get involved with|
（管制官４）
もう１機 突っ込んできます！
Another bogey
is closing in fast!
何！？
What?!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic)
（管制官５）これは…
It's... It's the DS-12! A debris retrieval ship!
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
DS-12 デブリ回収船です！
（ハキム）ToyBoxか
Toy Box, huh?
Don't mess with me,
you sons of bitches...
（フィー）ざけんな この野郎
食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow), やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
食らいやがれえーっ！
Suck on this!
ジャスト:just/perfect/exact, ミート:meat
ハッハー ジャストミート！
Kiss that one goodbye!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
（管制官１）
正体不明機 離れていきます
Bogey is moving off!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), コリジョン:collision, アラート:alert
（管制官２）
コリジョンアラート オフ
Collision alert, off.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 離脱[りだつ]:withdrawal/secession/separation, 噴射[ふんしゃ]:jet/spray/injection, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person
（管制官３）
緊急離脱噴射 停止します
Disengaging emergency
de-orbit burn.
W-We made it?
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
た… 助かった？
Both of them are
falling to Earth.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 地上[ちじょう]:above ground/surface|earth, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
（管制官４）
両機とも 地上に落ちます
ん？
The bogey and DS-12 are both
entering the atmosphere!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 共[ども]:first-person plural (or singular)|second or third person plural (implies speaker is of higher status than those referred to), 共[とも]:together with|same|both|, 大気圏[たいきけん]:the atmosphere, 突入[とつにゅう]:rushing into/breaking into|plunging into (war, etc.)
（管制官５）正体不明機 DS-12
共に大気圏に突入
They're burning up!
燃え尽きる[もえつきる]:to burn out
燃え尽きます
（司令）ハァ… フッ
保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954), ねえさん:elder sister|(vocative) young lady, 表彰[ひょうしょう]:public acknowledgment/public acknowledgement/public recognition
（ハチマキ）…で 保安庁が
ねえさんを表彰したいんだと
So anyway, the OSA says they want
to give you a commendation.
結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, オーライ:all right/OK
まあな 結果オーライって
ことなんだろうけど
Well, I guess it turned out
okay in the end...
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped, 運[うん]:fortune/luck
けどな
あんたが助かったのは運だ 運
But it was luck that saved
your ass over there! Luck!
やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
ムチャしやがって
You're a lunatic!
大気圏[たいきけん]:the atmosphere, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
ToyBoxは
大気圏には入れないんだぞ！
Toy Box wasn't designed to
enter the atmosphere, damn it!
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 放り出す[ほうりだす]:to throw out|to drop|to abandon|, 放り出す[ひりだす]:to expel/to eject/to push out, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
（ユーリ）どこか別の軌道に
放り出された可能性も
You might have been thrown off
into another orbit.
体当たり[たいあたり]:ramming attack/hurling oneself (at)|throwing oneself into (e.g. a role)
（タナベ）体当たりしたとき―
Did you even consider
what you'd do...
脱出[だっしゅつ]:escape/break-out|prolapse, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 庫[くら]:warehouse/storehouse/cellar, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
脱出機庫が壊れたらどうしようとか
考えないんですか？
...if the escape mechanism broke
when you rammed into it?
So tell me, what're we supposed
to fly in now, huh?
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
（ハチマキ）大体 これから
俺たち 何に乗りゃいいんだよ！
Hey, are you listening to me?!
Pay attention!
聞いてんのか！ おい こら！
Hey! You're the one who's always yelling
at me for being reckless, so what the hell?!
おい！
単細胞[たんさいぼう]:single cell|simple-minded person/one-track-minded person
いつも俺にムチャすんなとか
単細胞とか言ってるくせに何だよ
肝心[かんじん]:essential/fundamental/crucial, いちばん:number one/first|best
肝心なところで
あんたが いちばんムチャ…
When push comes to shove,
you're worse than I ever was!
（フィー）みんな
- You know, guys...
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, すばらしい:wonderful/splendid/magnificent
生きてるって すばらしいね
It's a wonderful thing to
be alive, don't you think?
Whatever!
（ハチマキ）知るか！
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Scenery with a Rocket
どうした？
What's wrong?
ぐっ があーっ
父親[ちちおや]:father, 兄貴[あにき, アニキ]:elder brother|one's senior|older man
（ハルコ）ほら
あの子の父親も兄貴も―
Look, that boy's father and big brother
are both astronauts.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
宇宙飛行士でしょう？
（ハルコ）何ていうか―
How can I put it?
勢い[いきおい]:force|influence|impetus|, 余る[あまる]:to remain/to be left over/to be in excess
勢い余っちゃってるのよね
九太郎(きゅうたろう)は
It's like Kyutaro
has too much energy pent up inside.
エンジニア:engineer
（九太郎）
俺はエンジニアになるんだ
I'm gonna be
an engineer.
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, エンジン:engine
さっさと大人になって
俺のエンジンで―
I'm gonna grow up fast,
and go on a day trip
to Mars with a rocket that I built!
火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 日帰り旅行[ひがえりりょこう]:day trip
火星 日帰り旅行を
やってやる
いっけ:a house/a home/a family, いっけ:prefix used to strengthen a derogatory adjective
いっけえーっ！
Go, baby, go!